In 2026, US unemployment rate is currently 4.3%.
If unemployment isn’t high,
why is the job market so awful?
It feels like it's never been harder to get a job.
The story is stranger than we might think.
Total employment.
Full time.
Part time.
Something is happening that
we haven't seen before.
Why do things feel so bad if the
unemployment rate is pretty good?
And why are thousands of companies posting job
listings they have no intention of filling?
Now the instinct for many people is to say:
It's AI! AI is causing all these problems!
And there's truth to that.
But, there's more going on here.
First, let's look at what AI is doing.
For one, lots of layoffs and redundancies.
1,500 from Meta, then another 8,000,
1,600 from Atlassian, 4,760 from PayPal,
16,000 from Amazon, 30,000 from Oracle!
So far this year, there's
been over 300,000 layoffs,
over 85,000 from tech alone. A
33% jump from this time last year.
Feels especially bad when CEOs refer to
layoffs as "lower-value human capital".
But more than that, AI is doing something else.
A 2026 study from BCG said that "over the next
two to three years, 50% to 55% of jobs in the US
will be reshaped by Ai. They retain the same or a
similar role but face radically new expectations
for how they work and what they produce"
Perhaps the most worrying part is entry
level jobs, which are starting to decline.
“Postings for entry-level jobs in the US
have plummeted by 35% in the last 18 months,
largely thanks to AI”
So it seems particularly bad for those trying to
get into the workforce through roles like these,
as the more basic tasks which require less
experience, are the ones most vulnerable to AI.
While it sucks to be working in tech right now,
this AI displacement doesn’t seem to have that
exponential growth people were saying it would.
"Initial evidence suggests that transitional
disruption from AI to date is not outpacing recent
technological changes. A similar pace to the years
after the start of the commercial computer era
(1984) and the commercial Internet era (1996) and
has not accelerated since the release of ChatGPT."
According to a survey of over 2,000 businesses
across 9 different countries, including
the US, "42% say AI has created jobs
across their organizations, 11% say it
has eliminated roles, and 35% report a
mix of both — netting to 77% reporting job
creation versus 46% reporting job loss"
Though, these are responses from companies,
so take that with a grain of salt.
But, there is something that shows
this is more than just AI, although
it's causing other problems we'll get to soon.
But AI doesn’t explain everything outside of tech.
A lot of jobs that can't be replaced by AI,
seem to be the ones in the worst situation.
Most assume blue-collar jobs would be doing great.
Some people are saying "Leave white-collar,
move into trades, you'll get a job".
"AI can't replace a plumber!"
And that's true, but that's not what's happening.
According to the Bureau of Labor Statistics,
the industries with the worst change in hiring
were trade, construction, and federal jobs.
Look at that graph. Information, professional,
and financial are showing fewer hires in the last
few years, but it's not just white-collar jobs.
Interestingly, healthcare is the industry with
the most explosive growth. Healthcare represented
47.5% of all job growth during 2025.
So what's going on, really?
With the current job market, a lot of
people have to re-evaluate their career.
It feels like the market is
redefining what a "job" even means,
and many are deciding to try running a business.
Business applications are at
record highs, and it makes sense!
More and more businesses are
being started out of necessity.
Building a passive income stream or starting a
side business is especially easy, with Printify.
Printify allows you to build your
very own ecommerce brand, in minutes,
and with no upfront investment.
Use it to build a passive income
stream or start a business.
But with Printify, you can really build
something of your own. Your own style.
Many are already using Printify to
earn five, or even six figures a month.
But even if you don't, it's still a great
way to give you another revenue stream,
and build some passive income.
So how does it work?
Choose from over 1300 high-quality products,
create your designs, publish
them, and then make money.
Printify takes care of fulfilment, so
there's no upfront cost in production.
Printify also integrates with the
biggest platforms, including Etsy,
Shopify, TikTok Shop, and many more.
Printify has the best prices on the market,
and with Premium, you get a further
20% discount on the entire catalogue.
They've already fulfilled over 60 million orders,
to over 200 countries and territories, with a
vast printing network across the US and Europe,
meaning fewer fees and faster shipping times.
Click the URL in the description
and use code Logically. Thank you to
Printify for sponsoring this video.
The labor market is in a very weird spot.
Unemployment isn't skyrocketing… but
new jobs added are historically low.
The total number of employees is mostly flat.
We're essentially in a "freeze". A
low-hire, but also… a low-fire market.
The hiring rate has gradually been
decreasing for the past few years.
In February 2026 this hit 3.1, about the same
as the collapse at the start of the pandemic.
Fewer companies are hiring people, though, it's
floated around this low point for a few years now.
But interestingly, also firing fewer.
Job openings are around 7 million. Down
a lot from a few years ago, and now, quite flat.
But, the job opening rate is also flat at 4.1%.
"The number and rate of layoffs and
discharges were little changed at 1.9
million and 1.2 percent. Layoffs and discharges
were little changed in all industries in March”
What's happening is that companies
aren't keen to hire more staff,
but aren't so keen to lay off people, as the
cost of replacing an employee is quite high.
Not only that, staff aren't keen
to leave their jobs right now.
Fewer people are keen to quit, which
creates even fewer job openings.
[Jerome Powell - Federal Reserve Chair]: "It's
an unusual and uncomfortable kind of a balance"
So, why are we in a low-hire, low-fire
situation? Well, a few reasons.
First, I think this is a pendulum swing after
Covid. There was a hiring boom after the pandemic,
and perhaps a lot of companies overhired.
Another is perhaps the recent tariffs.
These increased the costs of doing
business, more expensive parts,
lower margins, less profit.
Less desire to hire.
And it's likely to stay this way for a while.
[Mitchell Barnes, labor markets economist,
The Conference Board.]: "We should expect [low
hire low fire] to be more the norm going forward.
We have really been marking our calendars for the
first half of 2026 for really the full kind of
suite of the tariff impacts to really roll through
to businesses and, therefore, the labor market."
But this "low-hire, low-fire" market feels
especially bad, when we take another perspective.
Total jobs are steady,
But, this, along with a lot of "jobs added" stats,
misses one important nuance.
Full time, vs part time.
Full time.
Part time.
Full-time employment is either flat
or declining, part-time is going up.
"The labor market's success has been
fueled mostly by part-time-job growth,
rather than by the addition of full-time
jobs. The household survey suggests an
explanation for why Americans don't
perceive a robust labor market:
from their point of view, it isn't robust."
People might not be fired, but instead
their job might be "changed".
Moved from full time to part time.
Or a company might remove one full-time
job, but add two more part-time.
On the surface, it looks like
job growth, but it's not.
It's those who are unemployed and trying
to find work, who have it worse than ever.
The market is terrible for job hunters right now.
The actual process of getting a job is I'd say,
the worst it has ever been in
history. For a lot of reasons.
On our channel, we do all kinds of deep
dives into economics, companies, and finance.
There's a lot these stories
can teach us! So subscribe!
We're almost at 1 million now,
and you can help us get there!
Applicants per job posting in 2021, was about
45. In 2025, it was 95. More than double.
With a low hiring rate, more and more people
are applying for those jobs that are out there.
But, to make matters worse, many
of these jobs… don't even exist.
Essentially, you find a job listing,
from a real, legitimate company,
it has all the components of a normal job, like
responsibilities, experience needed, everything.
Looks legit! You write a cover
letter, send your resume,
maybe send a follow-up email a few weeks later.
Except… this job doesn't even exist.
These are ghost jobs.
Fake listings by real companies.
These have existed for a while,
but it's getting much, much worse.
Hires per job has fallen from 0.75 in 2018, to
below 0.5 in 2023. It's likely even lower today.
That means, less than HALF of job
postings will result in a hire.
Not that you're less likely to get that
job, that anyone will be hired for that job.
Surprisingly, those blue-collar jobs like
construction are being hit the worst.
Construction has it the worst, with 38%
of postings classified as ghost jobs,
followed by the art industry, and
then legal jobs at 34% and 29%.
Administration and support has seen a
negative 55% change in hires to job postings,
followed closely, again, by construction.
A 2024 survey found that "39% of hiring
managers admitted their companies posted fake
job listings in the past year. Among those,
26% said they posted one to three fake listings,
while 13% reported posting 75 or more."
So, why do this?
This seems like such a waste of time,
not just for applicants, but even the companies.
Well, there's a few reasons.
First, many publicly traded companies
will post fake job listings, not for jobs,
but as part of their PR strategy.
A 2024 study found that almost "1
in 4 recruiters were asked to keep postings
live "for visibility," not active hiring."
In another survey, 23% said it helped make the
company appear more stable during a hiring freeze.
If you look like you're hiring,
it implies you're growing,
doing well, and investment is more appealing.
For public companies, and even private companies.
But the second reason is even worse.
Another survey found 62% of hiring
managers use fake job listings, to
"have employees feel replaceable".
That's right. To make employees work harder, and
make them feel like they have less job security.
So, they're not just harming people looking
for work, but people inside the company.
The third reason is compliance requirements.
If the company already has someone in mind,
who's actually the perfect fit for the
job, who's worked there for a while,
they still have to go through the song
and dance of "pretending to hire".
Hiring within a company is a good
thing. Letting employees move up,
or maybe horizontally to a
more enjoyable job, is great.
But, they still create a job
listing, and waste everyone's time.
Recruiters and HR, to be honest, feel
like the villains in a lot of this.
People are using AI to apply for jobs, and
recruiters are using AI to hire people.
87% of companies and 99% of the Fortune
500 are using it in their hiring processes.
65% of recruiters rely on it daily and
24% use it as their primary hiring method.
81% for candidate sourcing,
73% for resume screening,
68% candidate communication via chatbots.
And you can see why.
It's 30-40% cheaper, and time to hire is up 50%.
But boy does it suck to go through.
No one is looking at any job applications,
and people are getting rejection emails,
before anyone even looks at their resume.
It's especially bad, because hiring doesn't
often fall to a team lead, but HR.
A manager might identify the best
possible candidate, but they
don't actually matter: HR does.
This is why you sometimes get weird skill
requirements on a job listing or in an interview,
because recruiters, often, have no
idea what the job actually involves.
Not to mention, it's especially bad with
some companies just lying on job listings.
Listing a job as "remote", then saying it’s 'an
onsite position and requires in-office presence",
Even if unemployment isn't growing much,
it's not a great time to be job hunting.
Especially as people are stuck
unemployed for longer and longer.
Many are applying for hundreds, or even
thousands of jobs, and getting nowhere.
This is made worse by companies abusing the job
postings to do something it was never meant for.
Something definitely needs to change,
potentially new legislation to ensure
the job market is doing what it's supposed
to: Giving people a chance to be hired,
giving companies a chance to find a new
employee, when there's actually a free position.
Not for PR, to scare employees, or just
because they legally have to post it.
One piece of good news though,
is that AI replacements
aren't working as well as many thought.
AI customer service, AI layoffs, are
actually backfiring for a lot of companies,
and CEOs are starting to regret it.
Click here to learn the rest of the story.